<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[John Firebaugh]]></title>
  <link href="http://jfirebaugh.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jfirebaugh.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-03-02T15:33:30-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://jfirebaugh.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John Firebaugh]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Xcode 4.3, homebrew, and autoconf]]></title>
    <link href="http://jfirebaugh.github.com/blog/2012/02/18/xcode-4-dot-3-homebrew-and-autoconf/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-18T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jfirebaugh.github.com/blog/2012/02/18/xcode-4-dot-3-homebrew-and-autoconf</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Xcode 4.3 no longer includes autotools. If you have installed Xcode 4.3 and
uninstalled the previous versions, you will no longer have <code>/usr/bin/autoconf</code>.
This isn&#8217;t usually a problem for installing homebrew formulae, since the
downloaded packages should come with <code>configure</code> pregenerated, but if you want
to use <code>brew install --HEAD</code> or are building a package from a source
repository, you may need it. Here&#8217;s how to get it:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>brew install https://github.com/adamv/homebrew-alt/raw/master/duplicates/autoconf.rb
</span><span class='line'>brew link autoconf</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>At some point in the near future, homebrew will probably add an autoconf formula.
At that point, you&#8217;ll be able to <code>brew install autoconf</code> directly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Visualizing SFpark Demand-Responsive Meter Rate Adjustments]]></title>
    <link href="http://jfirebaugh.github.com/blog/2011/09/03/visualizing-sfpark-demand-responsive-meter-rate-adjustments/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jfirebaugh.github.com/blog/2011/09/03/visualizing-sfpark-demand-responsive-meter-rate-adjustments</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On July 11th 2011, <a href="http://sfpark.org/">SF<em>park</em></a> announced the
first set of <a href="http://sfpark.org/how-it-works/pricing/">meter rate adjustments</a>.
Meter operational hours were divided into six distinct rate periods, and the hourly
price of metered parking in the project&#8217;s seven pilot areas was adjusted on a
block-to-block basis in response to parking demand during each period:</p>

<ul>
<li>+25¢ in periods of 80% or more occupancy</li>
<li>No change in periods of 60-80% occupancy</li>
<li>−25¢ in periods of 30-60% occupancy</li>
<li>−50¢ in periods of less than 40% occupancy</li>
</ul>


<p>I created this visualization using the <a href="http://mbostock.github.com/d3/">d3.js</a>
framework and data provided by SF<em>park</em>. Click for full size.</p>

<p><a href="http://jfirebaugh.github.com/sfpark/rates.html"><img src="http://jfirebaugh.github.com/sfpark/SFpark.png" alt="SFpark meter
rate adjustment visualization" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kernel Density Estimation with Protovis]]></title>
    <link href="http://jfirebaugh.github.com/blog/2011/04/03/kernel-density-estimation-with-protovis/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jfirebaugh.github.com/blog/2011/04/03/kernel-density-estimation-with-protovis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://bl.ocks.org/900762"><img src="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/7078234/KDE.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>A <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kernel_density_estimation">kernel density estimate</a> provides a
means of estimating and visualizing the probability distribution function of a
random variable based on a random sample. In contrast to a histogram, a kernel
density estimate provides a smooth estimate, via the effect of a smoothing
parameter called the <em>bandwidth</em>, here denoted by <em>h</em>. With the correct choice
of bandwidth, important features of the distribution can be seen; an incorrect
choice will result in undersmoothing or oversmoothing and obscure those
features.</p>

<p>Here we see a histogram and three kernel density estimates for a sample of
waiting times in minutes between eruptions of
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Faithful">Old Faithful Geyser</a> in Yellowstone National
Park, taken from R&#8217;s
<a href="http://stat.ethz.ch/R-manual/R-patched/library/datasets/html/faithful.html"><code>faithful</code></a>
dataset. The data follow a <a href="http://en.wikipedia%0A.org/wiki/Bimodal_distribution">bimodal distribution</a>; short
eruptions are followed by a wait time averaging about 55 minutes, and long
eruptions by a wait time averaging about 80 minutes. In recent years, wait
times have been increasing, possibly due to the effects of earthquakes on the
geyser&#8217;s geohydrology.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making sense of constant lookup in Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://jfirebaugh.github.com/blog/2011/01/21/making-sense-of-constant-lookup-in-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-21T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jfirebaugh.github.com/blog/2011/01/21/making-sense-of-constant-lookup-in-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In Ruby 1.8, constant lookup is mostly <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scope_(programming)#Lexical_versus_dynamic_scoping">lexically scoped</a>,
even when using <tt>class_eval</tt> or <tt>instance_eval</tt>.
That is, constant lookup always searches the chain of <em>lexically
enclosing</em> classes or modules. The first lexically enclosing class or
module is not necessarily the same as <tt>self.class</tt>:</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/790454.js?file=constants.rb'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>puts &quot;#{RUBY_VERSION}-p#{RUBY_PATCHLEVEL}&quot;

X = '::X'

class Foo
  X = 'Foo::X'

  def foo
    puts &quot;instance method: #{X}&quot;
  end
end

Foo.new.foo

f = Foo.new
def f.bar
  puts &quot;singleton method: #{X}&quot;
end
f.bar

Foo.class_eval do
  puts &quot;class_eval: #{X}&quot;
end

Foo.new.instance_eval do
  puts &quot;instance_eval: #{X}&quot;
end
</code></pre></noscript></div>


<p>Here&#8217;s the output on 1.8.7:</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/790510.js?file='></script>
<noscript><pre><code>1.8.7-p330
instance method: Foo::X
singleton method: ::X
class_eval: ::X
instance_eval: ::X</code></pre></noscript></div>


<p>Here we can see that within the lexical block defining <tt>Foo#foo</tt>, which
is enclosed by <tt>class Foo</tt>, <tt>X</tt> refers to <tt>Foo::X</tt>, while
in the lexical blocks used for the singleton method, <tt>class_eval</tt>, and
<tt>instance_eval</tt>, which are not in <tt>class Foo</tt>&#8217;s scope,
<tt>X</tt> refers to <tt>::X</tt>, the global constant.</p>

<p>However, in 1.9, the situation changes, and moreover, the behavior is
different between 1.9.1 and 1.9.2. Here&#8217;s the result of running <tt><a
href="http://rvm.beginrescueend.com/set/ruby/">rvm 1.9.1,1.9.2
constants.rb</a></tt>:</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/790511.js?file='></script>
<noscript><pre><code>1.9.1-p378
instance method: Foo::X
singleton method: ::X
class_eval: Foo::X
instance_eval: Foo::X
1.9.2-p136
instance method: Foo::X
singleton method: Foo::X
class_eval: ::X
instance_eval: Foo::X</code></pre></noscript></div>


<p>So, in 1.9.1, constant lookup in <tt>class_eval</tt> and
<tt>instance_eval</tt> proceeds from the receiver, rather than the lexically
enclosing scope. Particularly for <tt>class_eval</tt>, this turned out to be a
<a href="http://www.ruby-forum.com/topic/191672">problematic</a> <a
href="http://www.ruby-forum.com/topic/199317">change</a>, breaking existing
libraries that depended on the 1.8.7 behavior and making it hard to build DSLs
that behaved in predictable ways. Eventually, it was decided to <a
href="http://www.ruby-forum.com/topic/199317#871425">revert to the 1.8
behavior</a>, and this was supposedly implemented:</p>

<blockquote><pre>
&gt; [Matz] would like to revert all of instance_eval, instance_exec,
&gt; class_eval, and class_exec to the behavior of 1.8 (including class
&gt; variables). [...]

I have just commited it to the SVN trunk.
</pre></blockquote>


<p>I say &#8220;supposedly&#8221; only because as you can see, the 1.9.2 behavior still
differs from 1.8.7 in the case of <tt>instance_eval</tt>. Was this an
oversight, or was the revert later unreverted for&nbsp;<span
style="font-family: monospace;">instance_eval</span>? If so, what was the
rationale? I searched the mailing list and subsequent commits, but couldn&#8217;t
find an explanation. If anyone can shed light on the matter, I would
appreciate it.</p>

<p>As you can see, 1.9.2 also changed the behavior for singleton methods: the
receiver&#8217;s scope is now searched before the lexically enclosing scope. This
change makes sense to me, and I haven&#8217;t heard of it causing any problems.</p>

<p>Note that these rules apply to constant <em>definition</em>&nbsp;as well as
lookup. In 1.8 and 1.9.2, a constant defined in a class_evaluated block will
be defined in the enclosing lexical scope, rather than the scope of the
receiver. This is one of the things that makes <tt>Foo = Class.new { &#8230;
}</tt> not <em>quite</em> the same as <tt>class Foo; &#8230;; end</tt>:</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/790492.js?file='></script>
<noscript><pre><code>puts &quot;#{RUBY_VERSION}-p#{RUBY_PATCHLEVEL}&quot;

class Foo
  class Bar
  end
end

Baz = Class.new do
  class Quux
  end
end

puts Foo::Bar
puts Quux
</code></pre></noscript></div>


<p>The block passed to <tt>Class.new</tt> is effectively
<tt>class_eval</tt>uated, so in this example, the constant <tt>Quux</tt> ends
up defined at the top level. (And once again 1.9.1 is the exception: it
defines <tt>Baz::Quux</tt> instead.) This behavior can cause problems if you
are in the habit of defining test classes in RSpec <tt>describe</tt> blocks:</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/790496.js?file='></script>
<noscript><pre><code>require 'rspec'

describe &quot;a TestClass&quot; do
  class TestClass &lt; String
  end
end

describe &quot;other TestClass&quot; do
  class TestClass &lt; Integer
  end
end
</code></pre></noscript></div>


<p>Here <tt>TestClass</tt> winds up in the global scope, not the scope of the
RSpec example group that <tt>describe</tt> creates. If you have multiple specs
that define test classes with the same name, you may get collisions unless you
place each <tt>describe</tt> within a uniquely-named module or diligently
remove the constants in an <tt>after</tt> block. In the above example, you&#8217;ll
get the error &#8220;superclass mismatch for class TestClass&#8221;.</p>

<p>If you need to ensure a particular scoping is used (for example, if you need
to support 1.9.1 as well as 1.8.7/1.9.2), you can always be explicit about it
by prefixing constants with <tt>::</tt> (for global lookup), <tt>self::</tt>
(for receiver scope), or the fully qualified desired scope:</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/790500.js?file='></script>
<noscript><pre><code>require 'rspec'

describe &quot;a TestClass&quot; do
  class self::TestClass &lt; String
  end
end

describe &quot;other TestClass&quot; do
  class ::TestClass &lt; Integer
  end
end

module A
  module B
  end
end

describe &quot;third TestClass&quot; do
  class A::B::TestClass &lt; Integer
  end
end
</code></pre></noscript></div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Selenium on Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://jfirebaugh.github.com/blog/2010/12/22/selenium-on-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-22T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jfirebaugh.github.com/blog/2010/12/22/selenium-on-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The state of Selenium on Ruby is a bit confusing. Among the top google results for
<a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=selenium+ruby">&#8220;selenium ruby&#8221;</a> are several links that are badly out of date, and it&#8217;s
not clear which of the many <a href="http://rubygems.org/search?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;query=selenium">gems</a> are ones you would want
to use. This post aims to clear up some of the confusion.</p>

<p>First of all, you should be aware that there are two Selenium APIs: the original 1.0 API, called Selenium-RC, and a
newer 2.0 API called Selenium WebDriver. Internally, the two have quite different architectures. In a nutshell,
Selenium-RC is based around a Java &#8220;Remote Control&#8221; server process that launches the browser under test and manages
communication between the client process (the Ruby interpreter, in our case) and the browser. The browser is controlled
by injecting the &#8220;Selenium Core&#8221; JavaScript framework into the Browser&#8217;s built-in JavaScript interpreter. In contrast,
WebDriver requires no external process; the browser is launched directly, and controlled via means that vary from
browser to browser. For example, WebDriver controls Firefox via a custom Firefox extension.</p>

<p>Ruby has good support for both RC and WebDriver. The <a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/selenium-client">selenium-client</a> gem
(<a href="http://selenium-client.rubyforge.org/">docs</a>, <a href="https://github.com/ph7/selenium-client">source</a>) provides bindings for
the RC API, and the <a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/selenium-webdriver">selenium-webdriver</a> gem
(<a href="http://code.google.com/p/selenium/wiki/RubyBindings">wiki</a>,
<a href="http://selenium.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/docs/api/rb/index.html">docs</a>,
<a href="http://code.google.com/p/selenium/source/browse/#svn%2Ftrunk%2Frb">source</a>) provides bindings for the WebDriver API.
You will likely want to use one of these two gems, but which one? If you are using Selenium via a higher-level Ruby
library such as Webrat or Capybara, the choice will be made for you: Webrat uses selenium-client, Capybara uses
selenium-webdriver. If you want to access a Selenium API directly, I would generally recommend selenium-webdriver.
The WebDriver API provides several advantages, including multi-browser testing, page navigation, drag-and-drop, and
multi-frame and multi-window support. It recently released its
<a href="http://groups.google.com/group/selenium-users/browse_thread/thread/28ce2b37123a4e4d">first beta</a> and is where the
future of Selenium and Selenium on Ruby lies. It is, however, still beta software and sometimes changes its API in
aggravating ways. If stability is of paramount concern, stick with selenium-client.</p>

<p>You may find references to some other Selenium-related Ruby projects. The <a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/Selenium">Selenium</a>
gem (with a capital &#8220;S&#8221;) and its associated website <a href="http://selenium.rubyforge.org/">selenium.rubyforge.org</a> paved the
way for Selenium on Ruby, but today it is obsolete, as is the <a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/selenium-rails">selenium-rails</a>
gem which depends on it. Unfortunately they are still prominently featured in search results and on the
<a href="http://seleniumhq.org/projects/ruby/">outdated &#8220;Selenium on Ruby&#8221; page</a>, which doesn&#8217;t even mention selenium-webdriver.</p>

<p>The Selenium RC API relies on an external Java-based server process, and though the selenium-client gem provides rake
tasks to start and stop an RC server, it does not provide the actual jar file necessary to run the service. You can
either download and install it yourself, or install the <a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/selenium-rc">selenium-rc</a> gem, which
bundles it. You&#8217;ll sometimes see a gem that depends on selenium-client also depending on selenium-rc solely for the jar,
as the <a href="https://github.com/pivotal/jasmine-gem">jasmine</a> gem does. The selenium-rc gem has some Ruby code in it too, but
it more or less duplicates functionality that&#8217;s already part of selenium-client.</p>

<p>Finally there&#8217;s the <a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/selenium">selenium</a> and
<a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/selenium_remote_control">selenium_remote_control</a> gems, which provide functionality similar
to selenium-client and selenium-rc. They don&#8217;t seem widely used and at first glance I don&#8217;t see any reason to prefer
them to the more popular gems. Recent releases of the selenium-webdriver gem include the selenium-client code as well,
and personally, I hope that selenium-webdriver can usurp the &#8220;selenium&#8221; gem name and become the One True Selenium gem
for Ruby.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
